hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of holotalk
for the week of April 12 1998 our
special guest this week is Steve
Province from Blue Ridge holographics if
you're a new listener welcome aboard
this we call a talk begins transmission
of its broadcast to your computer with
real audio server software which opens
up the show to millions of other
listeners who could not access the show
before because you need the real audio
software I believe 4-0 and 5-0 this it
up to everyone else with the earlier
versions as well so if you're listening
to holotalk for the first time welcome
aboard
we're going to get to the Steve Province
interview in just a moment next week I'm
going to have a guest Todd Stark who is
director of exhibits and education at
the Discovery Center of Science and
Technology and he's going to fill us in
on the new traveling exhibit that's
coming to the center
here in Allentown Bethlehem and Eastern
Area from Pacific Science Center called
lasers and Holograms so we're going to
do a short interview with him next week
that'll go up on Sunday night so don't
forget to stop by and listen to that
okay I'm not going to come back on after
the Steve Province interview is
completed it's a interview that runs
about 25 minutes so what I'll do right
now is just thank you for tuning in and
looking forward to having you come back
as a listener week after week so this is
Frankie Freitas from holotalk and here's
the Steve Province interview
hello hi Frank Steve Steve
I'm doing quite all right so let's let's
start out you know there's a question
I've had for you and I want to ask you
you know this Show's been on uh since
November and I think you're probably the
first person that's actually a
professional holographer that has a
company that's manufacturing Holograms
I've had on here here's a question for
you there's a lot of kids that listen to
this show they listen to it in their
schools they listen to it in their home
computers now if you could give them
some tips would you advise them to
someday get involved with the field of
Photography or wouldn't you do that
um it depends on what kind of animal
you've got
[Music]
um holography is attracted a lot of
flakes over the year
um there's just something about Bright
Lights you know uh there's there's been
an awful lot of flaky people but
what what it takes to have fun in
holography is just creative desire that
that most people who ever saw Holograms
new at the first instant they ever saw a
hologram that they wanted to do it
and and it wasn't just a cure a mild
curiosity it was you know quite an
inspirational event a small Epiphany you
know they first saw a good hologram and
that drives
those who will be driven you know to
learn how to do it
but there's three different ways anybody
in any any Imaging field goes about
making a a living out of being a Creator
in any medium
is you kind of end up being part artist
part scientist and part businessman
and that's where a lot of the longevity
among various players in the field is
kind of falling apart there's some very
talented artists yeah in the field but
they don't have a lick of business sense
and there's some excellent scientists
who are unable to convey any emotion
into the technical exercise yes creating
a hologram yes
and there are a lot of businessmen who
may have you know pure greed profit
ground floor of a new industry in mind
who don't have a sufficient appreciation
for the science and or the art end and
those three worlds of art science and
business have often been in Collision
in the field of holography it's really
it's a communication media yes it it
ain't no special animal not in Virginia
I can say ain't
um
it's really a way of of
informing people now we happen to be
more in the commercial end
so we're typically trying to inform
people about uh to be candid you know of
a company's vanity
you know that they have arrived yes
they're uh with it and how to show that
through holography yes they they'll use
holography because it is is new and
exciting as a vehicle to promote
their view of themselves that they
themselves are Innovative and and look
at things different ways and uh so it's
a good reflection on companies who use
it
um but it is it's a communication Tool
uh as far as it's being used for us and
also with the good artists
I've had a few people on the show that
were involved with the education end and
they said that they wouldn't recommend
kids look into it as a job choice and
you know I know there's not much of an
industry out there but you know these
kids are in eighth grade and they love
photography they love lasers they
collect Holograms and someday they'd
like to grow up and go out into the
field uh develop some hard skills as far
as how to run the equipment and produce
the Holograms and bring some soft skills
along with it you know as far as
creative thinking and the thought
process and I just can't see sometimes
you know shutting them off like that to
tell them there's not a need to shut
them off but you know there's levels of
passion yeah
um that that relate to anything and
holography is a really good comparison
you know and and anybody listening has
probably met people who are audiophiles
you know into the very high-end ultimate
sound systems for which they can invest
you know tens of thousands of dollars
yes easily to chase down that final
one percent
of Noise free High Fidelity yes whereas
you can go down to Walmart and for 99
bucks you know pick yourself up a sound
system that will allow you to have a
rudimentary appreciation of uh of music
and so it it does it become a level of
passion the one neat thing about
holography although you know the the
entry ante because there are a few
Studios I mean you've gotta you've got a
Learning Studio
there's some out in San Francisco
the teach courses uh Jeff Murray's group
yeah
um
Jason sapan in New York City I believe
still teaches
but you know the number of of
Hands-On Educators uh to a person
wanting to take a course
is kind of limited yes it is and in the
University environment it's generally
taught just as a peripheral
segment to you know other studies
typically in the physics department
and you're not going to run into a lot
of physics professors who are going to
pick up pom-poms and steer people and
holography they find it to be an
interesting teaching vehicle
you know you can play
um in the game for you know somewhere
around fifteen hundred to two thousand
dollars
you know to build the the basic uh you
know uh
geopathic Lloyd cross you know
initiation system so the sandbox the
least expensive grade Edmund lenses
and and get a rudimentary understanding
you stand in front of uh
very impressive Margaret Binion piece
and look at your dark green two by two
inch reflection hologram you know you're
going to get a complex
uh there's a much higher Stakes of ante
unfortunately around the world the
universities Harbor
uh the type of equipment
you know that that can be available to
students high-end equipment yeah and in
the private sector it's it's a lot more
limited you know it used to be a lot
more open in this field uh from a
informative educational point of view as
well as an open door policy for people
who are anxious to learn and become
involved
uh before anybody made a buck yeah the
dollar reared its ugly head and all of a
sudden all this real free-flowing
information somehow closed up
uh sometime about the early 80s
that you know when the dollar uh
appeared into the scene people got a lot
more tight mouth where they used to you
know things became proprietary
they used to be considered discovery
and uh that that cast a different a
Different Light did you think we would
be further along in holography than what
we are today and and
why aren't we where we thought we would
be today do you have any feelings on
that primarily agreed yeah
like I say when when money started to
appear uh
patents
became weapons
instead of a mere acknowledgment of of
of of who thought this up first right uh
they became weapons to try to beat away
and stifle uh innovation
and competition
because there were dollars at stake you
know and as soon as uh the Visa card
came around
uh that pretty much set the whole game
off
there was big money at stake in
protecting uh the patents do you do
mostly in boss telegraphy there uh we do
not emboss we do origination okay
embossed Holograms voters Masters
tell us a little bit about Blue Ridge
while we have everyone's attention and I
wanted to let everyone know that there's
a link to Blue Ridge holographics
website that will be on the whole talk
page and you just click on that link you
don't have to sit there and stare at
your screen while you're uh listening to
the show because the real audio player
will play in the background while you
visit their website so why don't you go
now click on that link and Steve's going
to tell us a little bit about what
you're going to find there and what they
do well uh we didn't design our own
website but I think it came out pretty
okey-dokey
um
effectively Blue Ridge uh is sort of a
multiple entendra
originally the company since 83 had been
Steve province
and we started in the Santa Cruz
mountains
old Doobie Brothers country
up above Santa Cruz
and uh
the
earthquake started driving it's kind of
created
and also I had a long time associate
Nelson Poe
still with me who
the earthquakes were killing us well and
not out of fear of dying
but when you wake up and see a seventy
thousand dollar laser teetering on the
edge of a table uh ready to ready to
would have crashed with one more trimmer
you realize how fragile your livelihood
is
I watched a 1700 pound Newport table
literally dance across the laboratory
floor wow during the Loma Prieta Quake
was that your lab that got hard hit out
there uh and I read about I think it
might have been a holography news or
something they said one of the lab was
just Labs were just completely destroyed
I think light impression okay uh took it
on the chin uh with with a bunch of
stuff falling over uh we've been pretty
fortunate uh it was just mine are stuck
some some clean benches crashed and HEPA
filters got poked through and
it's like that but it wasn't those
events that actually spooked us from uh
you know working in Quake country it was
the bloody aftershocks
because a lot of the shots we do record
uh you know seven or eight different
elements or channels all done in a
sequence yes in a tightly registered
sequence
and all of a sudden one out of seven
no
explainable reason the shot wouldn't
come out yeah now photoresist as as you
may know is is a very slow
um very insensitive animal so it pushes
exposure times up into the minutes range
instead of the seconds range
and frankly after you'd spent you know
six hours getting through a sequence of
13 individual recordings
on a single plate
only to find one of them dropped out
because some little Tremor you couldn't
even feel had mucked it up you'd have to
start all over and after having to do
every job two or three times to get
lucky enough to avoid a myth
we just sort of said you know this is
counterproductive
so we loaded up the truck and we moved
from Beverly and uh came over to the
Blue Ridge Mountains wow
that's gorgeous here Charlottesville
Virginia it's stable this is the oldest
mountains in the whole country yeah they
ain't going nowhere
and uh frankly the the cost of
electricity of which we consume quite a
bit and the availability of water of
which we consume quite a bit
and also prices for Real Estate we're
much more favorable than they were in
California so we're Blue Ridge because
we're right here in the bosom of the
Blue Ridge Mountains
[Music]
oh cool
that's cool
what kind of jobs you take on from
people if someone was listening to the
show and they were thinking in the back
their mind you know I'd like to have a
couple Holograms done or something what
what type of jobs do you do for clients
well
in Boston is primarily a mass production
medium
so it doesn't really work out
people who say hey it'd be great to have
a custom embossed hologram on a couple
hundred of my business call
um
the person who picked up that ball and
ran with it is uh Peter Shire 82
000.
who you can also you can link to off of
my site he's going to be a guest coming
up I think in maybe four weeks I think
one low Run Productions yeah yeah Peter
filled an interesting niche
um that that he can accommodate people
who need fewer than a couple thousand
pieces of something and we've done jobs
uh where I mean
to be candid but mastering nut you know
runs around four or five thousand
dollars to get these things done
then in order to get a nickel die you
know to print the things you're looking
at another 500 000 or so
and by the time you've got somewhere in
the neighborhood of you know five to
seven thousand dollars anti involved
you're going to want to print a few of
them yeah for sure because because once
you've got that tooling out of the way
you're dealing with very inexpensive
credit
uh but for small quantities it doesn't
work we've done a few vanity things for
uh some companies who had some you know
big managers meeting and they really
wanted to impress the socks off them and
would do it for enough brochures to
cover a few hundred people coming a
meeting
but uh that sort of that level of
corporate vanity is few and far between
typically they're used for annual
reports things that are in the
neighborhood of 30 40 50 000 units and
up
and uh more and more and more small
security labels you know they're
everywhere yeah the dog bones are like
you're doing a lot of those in Asia
uh uh foreign you know things like bus
passes and and just little authenticity
items
but we're primarily a custom house we we
are not any law
any law stock image sales
so we're typically dealing with with
agencies
and we have a very effective uh broker
Network
and we're on very good terms with the
great majority of foil embossers around
the world
um
and that's primarily where our things
come from most people start with their
printer
and their printer doesn't know exactly
where to go so they go to their foil
supplier and their foil supplier leads
them to a design
or directly to us yeah and that's where
the majority of uh work comes from
and we stay quite busy during certain
seasons and it's not just a seasonal
animal
you never know what's going to go on
sometimes when the economy is ripping
people don't feel they need to advertise
as much because it's going great without
it
sometimes when there's a recession
people feel they need to advertise even
more sure yeah but it's a very
interesting I I can't even back to one
of the original questions which would
you recommend someone get into
holography
um
not just holography but any Independent
Business is like a yo-yo
and you've got to have a pretty hard
stomach for it oh yeah
it certainly is it's feast and famine it
is and some people just ain't got the
mental stamina
certainly when you're in what's trying
to be stable relationships you know wife
and kids and stuff it's kind of hard to
make people understand you know
the the ups and downs and lack of
regularity
uh you know present in holography which
is I think is especially a volatile
field
what's your take on the state of
holography right now I know in your
email you said you had a few comments
you'd like to make on holography in
general so the floor is yours well let's
see I guess I guess a couple of the
things are uh
I think I'd already gone over the greed
Factor that's that's the one part that
bothers me
um
uh but it's just the nature of business
there sure have been a lot of lawsuits
out there
um and you know those are rather
disheartening but again that's just an
indication that somebody has something
worth protecting yeah uh that's the
nature of that Beast I I hate to see a
lot of holographic Talent
uh turn themselves into attorneys you
know
all of a sudden when you know when
people are talking about Discovery and
they're not talking about a new image
they've got in mind they're talking
about litigations of a criminal trial
that they're involved in
um that speaks volumes in itself yeah
I'll throw out one thing I I I have
pretty strong opinions about a lot of
players in the field and and I said look
there there's there's frequently been
enough Bad Blood among people
players in the industry but I did want
to point out you know in case somebody
says gee Province doesn't really seem to
respect anybody that there are two
people
pretty much only in my opinion who
deserve any admiration or respect
in this industry
I could get take a guess who who would I
pick
someone from an embossing uh recording
guy's point of view
um who would you think I would have the
most respect for the first name that
comes to mind with me would be McGrew
no
um I think I was just referring to him
in the uh people becoming attorneys oh
okay creators now
I've always heard the story when he was
down in Norristown right you know before
he even went out to the West Coast and
the whole thing they were doing down
there with uh what the heck was the name
of the company that the Goldbergs had
down there and Scott and then say I was
involved with that company this was back
in the early days
whole ax exactly yeah so his was the
name that I always associated with it
right from the very beginning because
I'm just north of Norristown right so
that's that's why that name came well a
lot a lot of people that you know some
of the first ones you run into uh
are not always the the ones you stick
with yeah no I'd have to say rather than
the guessing game the the the two people
I most admire in this field are Ken
Haynes mm-hmm
uh formerly of American banknote and I'm
not sure currently but with Simeon uh
that he's always been uh brilliant
innovator
who sort of led the pack
uh in new methods of doing things uh
with Holograms especially relating to
mass production
and uh Michael Foster
who I probably would be remiss
and not putting down as you know a
genius
uh he was the first person to ever make
an embossed hologram really oh yeah okay
yeah back the old Museum of holography
back in New York back when they were on
20th Street uh
had a
little sample case or or gift case
things to sell and they had embossed
Holograms of things like the scuba diver
and uh
really neat multi-channel Superman comic
that Mike Foster had made I think as
early as 72. I saw that Superman piece I
think they had that in one of the
display cases they had their that there
permanently for a while uh well they
used to sell them they sell them for
about 10 bucks and they were hand pulled
you know yeah where did you do that man
do you have his own facility in New York
or something or no no Foster was uh uh I
think at the time he was teamed up with
uh Rich rollison okay uh out in Utah
yeah and then later in Los Angeles
but Foster soft embossing methods are
are
radically advanced
uh compared to most other embossing
methods I wish we could do more business
with them because they really really
look good and uh he's a chemist
that's primarily his background I see uh
but it's a darn good holographer too but
those are the those are really the two
people I put at the top
he's a whole lot of people
something that
I don't know I guess I could fall
there's always been because of the
equipment expense yeah and the risk of
high-end holography uh there's been a
lot of people who who've only made
uh a go of holography with what I call a
sugar daddy mentality I can't do it on
my own I won't start small
I need a partner
I need somebody else's money
in order to afford this and I'll bring
them in as a partner and we'll we'll
make a business of it and there's been a
lot of a lot of wrong marriages along
the line when somebody had the money and
somebody else had the desire and skill
and it's been sort of unfortunate
there's there's a few self-made people
it's easy to be jealous of the educators
because of all the equipment at their
disposal
but they didn't buy it yeah it's all
granted they didn't buy it yeah it's all
Grant and uh I don't know we've sort of
prided ourselves in being bootstrapped
kind of guy yeah
I'm over at Lehigh University now we
just opened the science museum I had you
know a couple hundred kids this weekend
for holography already
by the way you know you're one of the
hardest working guys in Show Business
yeah uh I mean you cover a lot of bases
and there's there's been a lot of gaps
created over the years between uh
Gallery closures the museum itself
[Music]
um the the number of
schools that do carry courses uh
following
through with you know education you know
broadening people's information base uh
and now you're taking it into the web I
have to complement your Enterprise well
thank you very much there's been a lot
of kids that have moved on and my
daughter who just started college this
year my oldest daughter's a physics
major and her physics Professor is a
student that I had in the early 80s that
started out with learning about lasers
and came into the studio and made some
Holograms she's married with her own
kids now she's still got the Holograms
on the wall but it's going generation to
generation now and that's you know and
the whole reason for the show was
basically just to fill a void of
information you know just give people an
opportunity like yourself
I can't you know to come on here and say
what it is you're doing you know in an
informal way where people can log on and
listen
with holography because it's so hard to
get any information about what's
happening that's true I'll give you a
basic life truth
applies to everything other than
holography too you only learn stuff
solidly by making mistakes and
one the brevity of a holography course
is unfortunate because there's so much
information to absorb
absorb that there could be a tendency to
be spoon fed and take what the teacher
has to say as an absolute law yeah do it
this way whereas some of the most
Innovative work in holography ever done
basically resulted from learning
something from the freedom to make a
mistake yeah it and it's it's changed
the course of Imaging uh so many times
Rudy Burke out uh do you think he just
envisioned the way some of his things
came out yeah I think there was a whole
series of happy accidents and boxes
ruined plates
before Rudy Got The Look he got and
we've everything we've figured out about
this game we've basically figured out my
try and error and making a lot of
mistakes I'll throw one other tip out
for any any uh student or amateur which
is don't take everything your teacher
says as an absolute
I would recommend to all novices
to throw away the beam splitter
every explanation of holography I've
ever heard
says
take your laser
split the beam into two parts with a
bean split yeah and I think you've
created a fundamental problem right out
of the gate
low powered lasers you just wasted a lot
of light yeah and actually if people
could practice and I think they'd find
great results in stability conservation
of the amount of light they had and
decreased exposure exposure Times by
using a sheer beam technique
where you remember that if spread out
expanded beam through an objective
is as many parts as you want it to be
you just have to take a mirror and make
let one part of it be referenced grab
another mirror and let it illuminate a
subject but take that little piece of
glass that's a beam splitter and put it
in a drawer for a while
you know yeah
all right well Steve I want to thank you
for being a guest taking the time out
you know for the listeners that log on
for the show I appreciate it very much
uh we're gonna cut it off now because we
try to keep the file size as the small
as possible this will probably wind up
being close to two Megs is the final so
you're gonna have to edit the heck out
of this no no editing we'll go up a
little every word you said is worth a
million bucks so we keep every word in
oh all right well before everybody
starts yawning we'll have to say good
night all right Steve thank you very
much for being on the show thanks Ryan
look forward to talking to you again
okay all right take care